Laercio Pires

laerciop@gmail.com // +351 915 875

Summary

Experienced Analytics Professional, dedicated to extract value from data in the past 13 years, designing solutions from automation to AI, aiming on marketing/business strategy outcomes.

Acknowledged digital business experience, leading data-centric projects in the biggest Latin America market (São Paulo/Brazil) for clients such as Unilever and Telefonica. Now digging into Portugal/EU data community and currently focused on build end-to-end data pipelines applying AI/ML for Advertising/Communication problems such as signal processing, NLP, and forecasting.

Interests: Business Analytics, Machine Learning, AI, Data Visualisation, Data Journalism/Storytelling Languages/Platforms: Python, SQL, Google Analytics/Tag Manager, GCP, Data Studio, PowerBl, Tableau. Specialities: Data Science, DataOps, Data Solution Design, Decision Science, Business Analytics

Experience



Data Science Lead

Publicis Groupe (Lisbon)

Jan 2020 - Present

Leading Data Science Discipline in the agency, being the technical reference for both internal community as for the client end, serving Media and Comms business unities. Hands on role, designing, implementing and maintaining data-centric solutions - from Audience Products to Community Analytics. Leading Data Science team (3 people), promoting adoption of up to date Tech and Process across the organization.

Working with clients from Automotive sector (Stellantis), Banking (Crédito Agricola, Bankinter) and FMCG (Bel Fromageries, Heineken).

AI/ML Projects Developing/Leading:

TV Scan: end-to-end pipeline to processes signal from TV Commercials and transform it into semantic features. The product is being very well received by the clients and helps the agency to position as an innovative business partner for them.

NLP tools: end-to-end pipeline that gathers data from Social Media platforms and transform in Graph databases. This product helped creating efficiency on data analysis and brought to the agency toolset an innovative way of looking into consumer.

Occupation Predictor: Automatized Regression Model that forecasts TV Advertising Occupation. After being implemented, helped Media Buyers to anticipate market movements and then have better negotiation advantage.

O Head Of Data Solutions

Gauge (São Paulo)

May 2018 - Sep 2019

Leading Gauge Data Solutions team (30+ people) to delivery best-in-class Analytics solutions to help business (such as Telefonica, Nike, Abbott and Fiat) make the best use of data.

Co-leading (in partnership with Telefonica team) implementation of Digital Analytics and Marketing Cloud Department- the biggest Digital Analytics initiative in Brazilian market, with ~50 people - involving a multidisciplinary Data team (with Data Engineers, Data Scientists, Analytics Translators, Data Architects and Data Visualization Specialists and Scrum Masters). This leadership role in this program, had two main focuses: 1. to create solid processes to organize operations and tactically manage team effort to tackle company challenges and 2. develop innovative solutions exploring the best of their tech stack could delivery.

ML Projects Developing/Leading:

Competitive Alerts: scripting tool for creating alerts with competitors promotions launch having OCR algorithm as its core. This initiative helped Telefonica Consumer Products Team to anticipate competition moves and implement tactical measures to answer to them.

Propension Audiences: scripting tool that fed Telefonica's Google Analytics with behavioral traces data. With these audiences Telefonica Online Store could improve their shopping understanding and their Digital Media results.

Data&Insights Director

Havas (São Paulo)

Aug 2017 - May 2018

Leading Data Science (5+ people) and Business Analytics teams (10+ people). Main focus in managing connections between Business and data science disciplines through the implementation of work methodology: tools for modeling consumer decision making and mapping growth drivers to feed marketing strategies. Working with PSA Group (Peugeot and Citöen brands).

ML Projects Developing/Leading: application of regression models with inference purposes.

foiz

Fbiz (São Paulo) – 2 positions in the same company

Consumer Insights Manager

Nov 2016 - Jul 2017

Help implementing Insights area in agency (3 people team), involving: consumer data analytics; media and consumer research. Main focus on clients prospecting/pitches.

Business Analytics Manager

Jul 2012 - Oct 2016

Leading a Business Analytics team (5 people) in order to delivery excellence in media/business results reporting, media and digital platforms optimization, and also competitive intelligence for clients such as Unilever, Motorola, Subaru and Pernod Ricard. Support on developing marketing strategy for agency clients.

ML Projects Developing/Leading: application of regression models with inference purposes.



DP6 (São Paulo) – 2 positions in the same company

Digital Data Analytics Coordinator

Jul 2011 - Jul 2012 (1 year 1 month)

Leading Marketing Accountability, Direct Response Media (Google Adwords), SEO and Social Listening projects for clients as Philips and Volkswagen.

Digital Data Analyst

Sep 2009 - Jul 2011 (1 year 11 months)

Working analysing digital platforms, digital media and business data, to supply actionable recommendations to marketing decision-makers.

Developed skills: Data wrangling (Advanced Excel Skills); Reporting and Data Visualization (Advanced Excel, Tableau); Google Analytics and Adobe Analytics (former Omniture); Google Adwords, Facebook Ads and other paid media analytics platforms (Doubleclick - former DFA -,Atlas).

Education



USP - Universidade de São Paulo

Major degree, Physics

2002 - 2003



Universidade Estadual Paulista Júlio de Mesquita Filho

Bachelor's degree, Social Sciences

2004 - 2009



ESPM Escola Superior de Propaganda e Marketing

Extension, Project Management

2011 - 2011

University of Michigan

Extension, Model Thinking (Economics)

Jun 2015 - Sep 2015

Licenses & Certifications

- Google Ads Search Certification Google
- G Advanced Google Analytics Google
- Machine Learning Devops Engineer Udacity
- Dataops Methodology Coursera
- Adobe Reports and Analytics Implementation Adobe